<section>
	<name>Definitions</name>
	<dl newline="true">
		<dt>Client</dt>
		<dd>
			The application that initiates the connection to
			a remote computer is called the client.
			The term client in this implementation guide,
			unless otherwise described, is referring to the client
			side of the Phoenix protocol,
			and not to any specific or general user interface.
		</dd>
		<dt>FIFO</dt>
		<dd>
			A First In First Out Queue.
			Data is pushed into the queue at the end of the line (Queue).
			And the oldest data is pulled from the front of the line (Queue).
		</dd>
		<dt>Queue</dt>
		<dd>
			A container for data that is like an ordered
			line that holds data until needed.
			Often referred to as a FIFO or FIFO queue.
		</dd>
		<dt>RPC</dt>
		<dd>
			<t>
				A Remote Procedure Call (RPC) is any method that
				allows a local computer to send data to a remote computer
				that results in the remote compute performing procedures
				on the behalf of the local computer.
				When combined with XDR it is sometimes called RPC/XDR.
			</t>
			<t>
				This term can be confused with a vendors specific
				implementation of RPC/XDR.
				This implementation guide is not referring to any specific
				implementation of RPC/XDR, it does
				use <xref target="RFC4506">XDR</xref> to convert data
				into a cross computer compatible format.
				And the Phoenix protocol is a form of RPC.
			</t>
		</dd>
		<dt>Server</dt>
		<dd>
			The application that is connected to by the client
			application is called the server.
			This guide is describing a generic Phoenix protocol server
			implementation.
		</dd>
		<dt>Thread</dt>
		<dd>
			<t>
				A Thread is somewhat like a program that run independently
				from the main program.
				Except they are within a single program.
				They allow the program to proceed in one area while
				another thread is perhaps blocked waiting for input.
			</t>
			<t>
				This is not to be confused with hardware threading.
				Some specific computer compiler may use hardware threading
				to accomplish this goal.
				Within this implementation guide, the term threading
				is referring to process threads and not hardware threads.
			</t>
		</dd>
		<dt>XDR</dt>
		<dd>
			The eXternal Data Representation or XDR, is a method
			of making sure that the data from one computer can
			be read and processed by what can be an
			otherwise incompatible device.
			See <xref target="RFC4506">XDR</xref>
		</dd>
	</dl>
	<t>
		<xref target="POSIX"/>
		<xref target="RFC0822"/>
		<xref target="RFC2119"/>
		<xref target="RFC4506"/>
		<xref target="RFC5234"/>
		<xref target="RFC8174"/>
		<xref target="RFC8446"/>
		<xref target="RFC9051"/>
		<xref target="rpcgendocs"/>
		<xref target="rpcgenopensource"/>
		
	</t>
</section>
