<section anchor="ADMIN_SUMMARY">
	<name>Administration Commands Summary</name>
	
	<t>
		Implementations are not required to implement any ADMIN command.
		A client will know the server supports one or more ADMIN
		commands when it gets its post authentication capability command
		from the server.
	</t>
	<t>
		Administrative command can be used to configure, audit, and manage
		the remote endpoint.
		Administrative command can be used to configure, audit, and manage
		user access.
	</t>

	<section anchor="ADMIN_CAP">
		<name>Administration Capability Definitions</name>
		<t>
			Implementations MUST NOT send the ADMIN capability
			in the pre authorization CAPABILITY list.
		</t>
		<t>
			Implementations that support any administration command
			MAY include ADMIN capability in the post authentication CAPABILITY list.
			An implementation may decide that only specified and
			authorized users may issue administrative commands and
			send only those authenticated users the ADMIN capability.
		</t>
		<t>
			The ADMIN capability include the list of ADMIN commands the user is
			allowed to perform.
			For example, if a user only has permission to only view user lists, then
			only the USER_LIST ADMIN capability will be provided.
		</t>
		<t>
			The capability name is also the command name to use
			when invoking that capability.
		</t>
		<t>
			When a user attempts to send a commmand they are not authorized
			to send, the remote endpoint will reply with a NotSupported command
			with its sequence number set to the sequence number from offending
			command.
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="ADMIN_USER">
		<name>Administration of users.</name>
		<t>
			The following operations are defined for administration.
		</t>
		<table>
			<thead>
				<tr><th>Command and Capability Name</th><th>Brief Description.</th></tr>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<tr>
					<td>USER_CREATE</td>
					<td>
						May create a new user.
						And also the command to create a user.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>USER_DELETE</td>
					<td>
						May delete a user.
						And the command to delete a user.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>USER_RENAME</td>
					<td>
						May rename a user.
						And the command to rename a user.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>USER_LIST</td>
					<td>
						May list users and their capabilities.
						And the command to list users.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>USER_PERMISSIONS</td>
					<td>
						May update other users permissions.
						And the command to view and set user permissions.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_SHUTDOWN</td>
					<td>
						May shutdown the server.
						And the command to shutdown the server.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_LOGS</td>
					<td>
						May view the server logs.
						And the command to view server logs.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_KICK_USER</td>
					<td>
						May logout a user. And limit when they can use the server again.
						And the command to kick and limit a user.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_MANAGE_BANS</td>
					<td>
						May manage IP and user bans.
						And the command to manage ban users an IP addresses.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_VIEW_STATS</td>
					<td>
						May view server statistics.
						And the command to view statistics.
					</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>SERVER_CONFIGURE</td>
					<td>
						May configure the server. If sent with a VIEW_ONLY
						parameter, then the user may only view the configuration
						information.
						And the command to view and alter the server configuration
						information.
					</td>
				</tr>
			</tbody>
		</table>

	</section>
</section>
