<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->
<section anchor="AUTHANONYMOUS" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<name>Authentication - ANONYMOUS</name>
	<t>
		ANONYMOUS is both a capability and a command.
	</t>
	<section anchor="AUTHANONYMOUS-CAPABILITY">
		<name>Authentication - AUTHANONYMOUS - Capability</name>
		<t>
			When sent as a capability, a true or false value
			follows.
			When true, it means that anonymous login is supported.
			When false, it means that anonymous login is not supported.
		</t>
		<t>
			The highest bit is set to zero (0) which indicates
			this is a Phoenix defined capability, and
			not a vendor created and known capability.
			Followed by the 31-bit capability value.
		</t>
		<figure>
			<name>Capability - AUTHANONYMOUS</name>
			<artset>
				<artwork type="ascii-art" src="ANONYMOUS-00.txt"/>
				<artwork type="svg" src="ANONYMOUS-00.svg"/>
			</artset>
		</figure>
	</section>

	<section anchor="AUTHANONYMOUS-COMMAND">
		<name>Authentication - AUTHANONYMOUS - Command</name>
		<t>
			Once the connection is made the server sends its pre authentication
			capability list to the client.
			If AUTHANONYMOUS is included in that list, then the client
			may initiate an AUTHANONYMOUS login.
		</t>
		<t>
			If the client has already had a relationship with the server,
			then the client may send the AUTHANONYMOUS command to the server
			before receiving the servers capability list, and only if AUTHANONYMOUS
			was the last successful authentication method to that server.
		</t>
		<t>
			If the server does not support (or no longer supports) an AUTHANONYMOUS
			command, it will reply with a NotSupported packet with the
			sequence number	the same as in the AUTHANONYMOUS login request.
		</t>
		<t>
			After the server receives an AUTHANONYMOUS, and if it supports it,
			it allows the connection and considers the user a valid
			anonymouse user.
		</t>
		<t>
			On failure the server replies with a AUTHANONYMOUS packet,
			with the sequence number the same that was in the
			ANONYMOUS command it received.
		</t>
		<t>
			On success the server replies with a post authentication
			capability command.
		</t>
			
		<figure>
			<name>Capability - AUTHANONYMOUS</name>
			<artset>
				<artwork type="ascii-art" src="ANONYMOUS-01.txt"/>
				<artwork type="svg" src="ANONYMOUS-01.svg"/>
			</artset>
		</figure>

		<section>
			<name>Authentication - ANONYMOUS - ABNF</name>
			<figure>
				<name>Authentication - ANONYMOUS - ABNF</name>
				<xi:include href="include/10-AuthAnonymous-ABNF.xml"/>
			</figure>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<name>Authentication - ANONYMOUS - XDR</name>
			<figure>
				<name>Authentication - ANONYMOUS - XDR</name>
				<xi:include href="include/10-AuthAnonymous-XDR.xml"/>
			</figure>
		</section>
	</section>
	
</section>
