<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->

<section anchor="AUTH_SUMMARY" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<name>Authentication Commands Summary</name>
	<t>
		The first thing a client must do, is authenticate
		with the server.
	</t>
	<t>
		Some users may also be administrators.
		In those cases the user and client may wish to do further
		authentication steps.
		A user may wish to temporarily step up their authentication
		level to perform some operations, then step back down
		to do their personal operations.
	</t>
	<t>
		A server may if it wishes include AUTH capabilities in
		the CAPABILITY_POST command.
		It can decide which authenticated users can or must use
		additional authentication.
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			Some user accounts can be user only, without administrative
			abilities of any kind.
			Their CAPABILITY_POST list will not include any ADMIN capabilities.
		</li>
		<li>
			Some user accounts can be administrative only, and are limited
			to CAPABILITY_POST actions that only include ADMIN capabilities.
		</li>
		<li>
			Some user accounts can be a normal user, with the ability
			to step up their account to be able to do administrative actions.
			While in stepped up mode, they are not able to act as their
			original user account.
			These users will get one or more AUTH capabilities in
			their CAPABILITY_POST list.
		</li>
		<li>
			And some user account can be allowed all operations.
			This protocol does not limit users.
			This protocol enables user permissions to be configured.
		</li>
	</ul>

	<section>
		<name>Authentication Failure</name>
		<t>
			If the authentication fails, then the server replies
			back with a CAPABILITY_PRE with the sequence
			number the same as in the authentication request.
		</t>
		<t>
			Or The server replies with a NOT_SUPPORTED when the authentication
			method is not supported, and with the sequence
			number the same as in the authentication request.
		</t>
		<figure>
			<name>AUTHCERT_USER</name>
			<artset>
				<artwork align="center" type="ascii-art" src="AuthSummary-00.txt"/>
				<artwork align="center" type="svg" src="AuthSummary-00.svg"/>
			</artset>
		</figure>
	</section>

</section>
