<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->
<section anchor="AUTHMD5" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<name>Authentication - MD5</name>
	<t>
		AUTHMD5 is both a capability and a command.
	</t>
	<section anchor="AUTHMD5-CAPABILITY">
		<name>Authentication - MD5 - Capability</name>
		<t>
			When sent as a capability, a true or false value
			follows.
			When true, it means that AUTHMD5 is supported.
			When false, it means that AUTHMD5 is not supported.
		</t>
		<t>
			The highest bit is set to zero (0) which indicates
			this is a Phoenix defined capability, and
			not a vendor created and known capability.
			Followed by the 31-bit capability value.
		</t>
		<figure>
			<name>Capability - AUTHMD5</name>
			<artset>
				<artwork align="center" type="ascii-art" src="MD5-00.txt"/>
				<artwork align="center" type="svg" src="MD5-00.svg"/>
			</artset>
		</figure>
	</section>

	<section anchor="AUTHMD5-COMMAND">
		<name>Authentication - MD5 - Command</name>
		<t>
			Once the connection is made the server sends its pre authentication
			capability list to the client.
			If AUTHMD5 is included in that list, then the client
			may initiate an AUTHMD5 login.
		</t>
		<t>
			If the client has already had a relationship with the server,
			then the client may send the AUTHMD5 command to the server
			before receiving the servers capability list, and only if AUTHMD5
			had been successful in the past, to that server.
		</t>
		<t>
			If the server does not support (or no longer supports) an MD5
			command, it will reply with a NotSupported packet with the
			sequence number	the same as in the MD5 login request.
		</t>
		<t>
			After the server receives an AUTHMD5, and if it supports it,
			then it attempts to verify the provided information.
			One of two replies are possible, success, or failure.
		</t>
		<t>
			On failure the server replies with a AUTHMD5 packet,
			with the sequence number the same that was in the
			AUTHMD5 command it received.
			With the login and password fields empty and their
			lengths set to zero.
		</t>
		<t>
			On success the server replies with a post authentication
			capability command.
		</t>
			
		<figure>
			<name>Capability - AUTHMD5</name>
			<artset>
				<artwork align="center" type="ascii-art" src="MD5-01.txt"/>
				<artwork align="center" type="svg" src="MD5-01.svg"/>
			</artset>
		</figure>

		<section>
			<name>Authentication - MD5 - ABNF</name>
			<figure>
				<name>Authentication - MD5 - ABNF</name>
				<xi:include href="include/09-AuthMD5-ABNF.xml"/>
			</figure>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<name>Authentication - MD5 - XDR</name>
			<figure>
				<name>Authentication - MD5 - XDR</name>
				<xi:include href="include/09-AuthMD5-XDR.xml"/>
			</figure>
		</section>
	</section>
	
</section>
