<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->

<section anchor="CAPABILITY"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<name>Capability Commands Summary</name>
	<t>
		Capabilities are attributes of both a client and server
		implementation.
		Some may provide a superset or subset when compared
		to other implementations.
		This can be done to split workload or just because
		they specialize in specific operations.
	</t>
	<t>
		A capability is a 31-bit integer.
		Plus a 1-bit identifier signifying if it is a Phoenix capability
		or vendor specific capability, for a total of 32-bits.
	</t>
	<t>
		This specification describes several capabilities.
		Some are described in other sections, and some are
		described in this section.
		See appendix XREF-TODO for a complete list in this specification.
	</t>

	<t>
		Capabilities from the server arrive twice.
		Once before the user is authenticated (CAPABILITY_PRE),
		and once after (CAPABILITY_POST).
	</t>
	<t>
		Capabilities from the client may be sent, zero, once, or twice
		per authentication process.
		Optionally once included with the AUTH command packet (CAPABILITY_PRE),
		to inform the	server of any required vendor or authentication
		specific information.
		And optionally once after the user is authenticated (CAPABILITY_POST).
	</t>
	<t>
		There is no requirement that a server provides
		an authentication method for any client.
		There is no requirement that a server provide
		any non-vendor capability for any client.
		They could be configured to only allow vendor
		specific authentication or only vendor specific commands because they
		are not servers open to the public and require
		non standard authentication methods,
		or only from clients providing a correct CAPABILITY_PRE
		value.
	</t>
	<t>
		Table <xref target="PreAuthCap"/> lists the CAPABILITY_PRE
		capabilities.
	</t>
	<table anchor="PreAuthCap">
		<name>Capabilities - CAPABILITY_PRE</name>
		<thead>
			<tr>
				<th>Name</th>
				<th>Value</th>
				<th>Data Type</th>
				<th>Required or Optional</th>
				<th>Description</th>
			</tr>
		</thead>
		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td>AUTHANONYMOUS</td>
				<td>%x26:31</td>
				<td>Boolean</td>
				<td>Optional</td>
				<td>
					<t>
						No authentication required.
						An example usage could be a shared company
						bulletin board where most employees had
						view only access to the messages.
						And perhaps the server only allowed
						company local IP addresses to use this
						authentication method.
					</t>
					<t>
					</t>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>AUTHMD5</td>
				<td>%x10:31</td>
				<td>Boolean</td>
				<td>Required</td>
				<td>
					<t>
						Authenticate by providing an MD5 password.
					</t>
					<t>
						If not supported, the value must be false.
						When supported, the value must be true.
					</t>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>AUTHCERT</td>
				<td>%x11:31</td>
				<td>Boolean</td>
				<td>Optional</td>
				<td>
					<t>
						Authenticate by providing a certificate.
						This can be used for humans, and can be used
						by automated connections.
					</t>
					<t>
						Not being provided is the same as false.
						May have a true or false value as needed.
					</t>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>VENDOR_ID</td>
				<td>%x12:31</td>
				<td>string</td>
				<td>Optional</td>
				<td>
					<t>
						VENDOR_ID includes a vendor ID
						string that can be used to help the server determine
						if it will send a post-authentication ADMIN capability.
					</t>
					<t>
						The specific string value is determined by the server
						implementation and is out of scope for this specification.
					</t>
				</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>
			
	<t>
		Table <xref target="PostAuthCap"/> lists the CAPABILITY_POST
		capabilities.
		Post-Authentication capabilities are sent to the client after
		a user authenticates.
	</t>
	<table anchor="PostAuthCap">
		<name>Capabilities - CAPABILITY_POST</name>
		<thead>
			<tr>
				<th>Name</th><th>Value</th><th>Description</th>
			</tr>
		</thead>
		<tbody>
			<tr>
				<td>x</td><td>x1</td><td>x2</td>
			</tr>
		</tbody>
	</table>

	<xi:include href="VendorID.xml"/>
</section>

