<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->

<section xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<name>Commands</name>
	<t>
		The endpoint that initiates the connection is called the client.
    The endpoint that is connected to, is called the server.
    The client is the protocol authority, and the server responds
    to client commands as configured or instructed by the client.
  </t>
	<t>
		This section provides an overview of the basic commands.
		Each command has a detailed section in this specification.
	</t>
	<t>
		When a command is sent to the remote endpoint and received,
		the remote endpoint determines if the connection is authenticated
		or authorized to perform the command.
		If not supported, or not authorized, a NotSupported command
		is send as a reply.
		The NotSupported command sent back has the same Sequence number 
		that was in the original command.
	</t>
	<t>
		Many commands are only valid after authentication.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the client connects to a server it immediately sends
		a CAPABILITY_PRE list to the server.
		Or the client sends an AUTH command.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the server gets a new connection followed by
		a pre authentication capability command, it immediately sends
		its pre authentication capabilities to the client.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the client and server have had a relationship, the
		client may send an Auth Command to initiate the authorization
		and does not send its pre authentication capability list
		to the server.
		It then waits for the Auth reply from the server.
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			If the client gets an Auth reply that is positive,
			it sends its post authentication capability list to the server.
		</li>
		<li>
			If the client gets an Auth reply that is negative,
			it sends its pre authentication
			capability list to the server.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<t>
		When a servers first received packet is a Auth command,
		It processes the Auth command and sends the Auth reply.
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			If the Auth reply is positive, then it also sends it
			post authentication capability list.
		</li>
		<li>
			If the Auth reply is negative, then it sends its
			pre authentication capability list to the client.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<t>
		A server may automatically send its pre authentication
		capability list to the client upon initial connection.
		Or it may wait to see if it gets a pre authentication
		capability list, or an Auth command.
	</t>
	<t>
		If the client sends an Auth command as its first packet,
		it may get the pre authentication capability from the server
		before the Auth reply. Simply process both.
	</t>
	
	<xi:include href="ProtocolSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="AdminSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="AuthSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="AuthAnonymous.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="AuthCert.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="AuthMD5.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="CalendarSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="CapabilitySummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="EMailSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="Folder.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="KeepAliveSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="PingSummary.xml"/>
	<xi:include href="SMimeSummary.xml"/>

</section>
