  <dl newline="true">
    <!-- Omit newline="true" if you want each definition to start on the sa\
me line as the corresponding term -->
		<dt>AdminCmd</dt>
		<dd>
			A general term for any administrative command.
			Administrative and auditing operations.
			This list includes commands for authorized users to configure,
			query logs, errors,	possibly user activity.
		</dd>
		<dt>AuthCmd</dt>
		<dd>
			A general term for any authentication command.
			Authentication and authorization operations.
			These operations authenticate users and verity their authorization
			access.
		</dd>
		<dt>CMD</dt>
		<dd>
			A specific protocol operation, or command.
			They are broken down into, AdminCmd, AuthCmd, FileCmd,
			and ProtoCmd.
		</dd>
    <dt>Command, CMD</dt>
    <dd>
			Each packet contains a command.
			This command is also in the reply to the command.
			Not all commands have a reply.
			These are called a CMD or command.
		</dd>
		<dt>FileCmd</dt>
		<dd>
			A general term for any file command.
			File and folder operations.
			This include creating, getting, modifying, deleting, moving,
			and renaming files.
		</dd>
    <dt>Media Type</dt>
    <dd>
			Each MIME object has a media type that identifies the
			content of the object.
			This specification does not add, remove, or alter any MIME media type;
		</dd>
    <dt>MIME</dt>
    <dd>
			This protocol transports MIME objects.
			This specification does not remove or alter any MIME objects;
		</dd>
		<dt>Packet</dt>
		<dd>
			A packet is a blob of data that has a header (its length)
			followed	by a Phoenix command with all
			of its values and parameters.

			Packets flow in both directions and asynchronously.
			Commands can be sent while still waiting for other replies.

			Each endpoint may send commands to the other endpoint without
			having to be prompted to send information.
		</dd>
    <dt>Parameter</dt>
    <dd>
			Most commands have values that are associated with them.
			These values are called parameters.
			For example, the create folder command has the name of the new
			folder to be created as a parameter.
		</dd>
    <dt>ProtoCmd</dt>
    <dd>
			A general term for all protocol commands.
			This also includes commands that do not fall into one of
			the other catagories described here in this definistions section.
		</dd>
    <dt>SEQ, Command Sequence, CMD_SEQ</dt>
		<dd>
			Each command has a unique identifier, a sequence number.
			All replies to a command include the same sequence number
			as the original command.
			In this way replies can be matched up with their original command.
		</dd>
		<dt>SSL</dt>
		<dd>
			For the purpose of this specification, SSL is interchangable
			with TLS.
			This document uses the term TLS.
			The sample implementation uses both SSL and TLS because
			the legacy UNIX, Linux, Windows, and OpenSSL code
			uses the term SSL as well as TLS.
		</dd>
		<dt>TLS</dt>
		<dd>
			A way of securely transporting data over the Internet.
			See RFC-xxxx.
		</dd>
    <dt>XDR</dt>
    <dd>
			RFC-4506 specifies a standard and compatible way to transfer
			binary information.
			This protocol uses XDR to transmit a command, its values
			and any parameters and replies.
			The MIME data, the payload, is transported as XDR opaque,
			and is unmodified.
		</dd>
  </dl>
