<section anchor="KEEPALIVE_SUMMARY">
	<name>KeepAlive Command Summary</name>

	<t>
		The KeepAlive command is sent to the server from the client.
		It requests the server not time out.
		The server may honor or ignore the request.
	</t>
	<t>
		The Phoenix protocol is designed to transfer data and a server
		may handle a small subsets of what is possible.
		Which is why the server decides what is an important command
		while determining idle timeout.
	</t>
	<t>
		When the server sends the post authentication capabilities to the
		client, it includes an IdleTimeout capability that includes the
		number of seconds it allows for idle time.
		If no significant action has been taken by the client, as determined
		by the server, in that time	the server may timeout and close the connection.
	</t>
	<t>
		The KeepAlive command tells the server that the client wishes the
		server not to time out as long as a KeepAlive or other command
		is sent to the server before IdleTimeout seconds have passed.
	</t>
	<t>
		An IdleTimeout capability can be a positive number, zero, or
		a negative number.
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			A positive number is the maximum idle time in seconds before the server
			terminates the connection.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the IdleTimeout is zero (0), the server does not timeout.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the IdleTimeout is less than zero (&lt; 0), it means it ignores
			KeepAlive and it will idle out in the absolute value of the IdleTimeout
			value in seconds.
			For example, a value of (-300) means it will ignore KeepAlive
			and timeout when the server determines nothing significant has
			happened in 5 minutes (300 seconds).
		</li>
	</ul>
	<t>
		Servers that are not threaded or can not reply to simultaneous
		or overlapping commands, MUST set their IdleTimeout to zero (0)
		or a negative number.
	</t>
	<t>
		Clients MUST NOT send KeepAlive commands to a server
		that has an IdleTimeout of zero (0) or negative (&lt; 0).
	</t>
	<t>
		Clients MUST NOT send KeepAlive commands to the server until
		at least 75% of the idle time has passed since the last
		command has been sent to the server.
	</t>
	<t>
		A server may terminate a connection if the server implementation
		determines that KeepAlive commands are arriving to quickly.
	</t>
</section>
