<section anchor="PING_SUMMARY">
	<name>Ping Command Summary</name>

	<t>
		The ping command only sent when the client implementation
		has determined it has waited too long for a command reply.
		The ping command is only initiated from the client.
		It is not valid for the server to send a ping command to a client.
	</t>
	<t>
		The ping command MUST NOT be the first command sent to the server.
		It should only be sent when the client implementation determines
		it has waited too long for a reply.
	</t>
	<t>
		If the server supports the ping command, then a PING capability
		is sent in the pre authentication capability command.
	</t>
	<t>
		Sometimes servers are unavailable and can go down.
		A server could be down for maintenance, or in a shutdown mode.
		It might limit the number of simultaneous connections.
		It might be very busy.
		The packets might not be making it to the server because of
		network issues.
	</t>
	<t>
		When a ping command is received by the server:
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			When the server did not send PING capability to the client.
			Then the server replies with a NotSupported packet
			with the sequence number the same as in the ping command.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the server has not yet received an authentication
			command, the server replies with a NotSupported packet
			with the sequence number the same as in the ping command.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the server has received an authentication command,
			and has not yet replied to an authentication command.
			Then the server sends a ping reply, with the same sequence
			number that was in the ping command.
			This could happen when the client implementation had determined it
			has waited too long	for an authentication reply.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the client is authenticated,
			and when the server is available for processing commands.
			Then the server replies with a ping reply with the same sequence number.
			This could happen when the client implementation had determined it
			has waited too long	for an expected reply.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<t>
		If the server is alive and not available, the server
		will reply with a NotSupported command, with its sequence
		number set to the sequence number in the ping command.
	</t>
	<t>
		If a connected and authenticated client has been waiting for a reply
		or for some other reason needs to determine if the server is still
		available. It can send a ping command.
		If the server is still available, it sends a ping reply.
		If it is no longer available for any reason, it sends a NotSupported
		reply.
	</t>
	<t>
		Endpoints MUST NOT send a ping command if they are awaiting
		the results of a previously sent ping command.
	</t>
	<t>
		Endpoints MUST NOT send more than two ping commands per minute.
	</t>
	<t>
		Clients and servers must give priority to ping commands.
		If possible, reply as soon as it receives the command.
	</t>
	<t>
		The server MAY consider too many ping commands as a malfunctioning
		or malicious client and terminate the connection.
	</t>
	<t>
		Servers that are not threaded or can not reply to simultaneous
		or overlapping commands, MUST NOT include PING in
		their capability command.
	</t>
</section>
