<!-- Copyright 2025 RiverExplorer LLC and Douglas Mark Royer -->

<section anchor="PING_SUMMARY">
	<name>Ping Command Summary</name>

	<t>
		The ping command is only sent when the client implementation
		has determined it has waited too long for a command reply.
		The ping command is only initiated from the client.
		It is not valid for the server to send a ping command to a client.
	</t>
	<t>
		A ping command must not be sent before a successful authentication.
	</t>
	<t>
		The ping command MUST NOT be the first command sent to the server.
		It should only be sent when the client implementation determines
		it has waited too long for a reply.
	</t>
	<t>
		If the server supports the ping command, then a PING capability
		is sent in the CAPABILITY_POST command.
	</t>
	<t>
		Sometimes servers are unavailable and can go down.
		A server could be down for maintenance, or in a shutdown mode.
		It might limit the number of simultaneous connections.
		It might be very busy.
		The packets might not be making it to the server because of
		network issues.
	</t>
	<t>
		When a ping command is received by the server:
	</t>
	<ul>
		<li>
			When the server did not send PING capability in the
			post authentication capability list to the client.
			The server ignores the PING command.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the connection is not authenticated,
			The server ignores the PING command.
		</li>
		<li>
			When the client is authenticated,
			and when the server is available for processing commands.
			Then the server replies with a ping reply with the same sequence number.
			This could happen when the client implementation had determined it
			has waited too long	for an expected reply.
		</li>
	</ul>
	<t>
		If the server is alive and not available, the server
		will reply with a NotSupported command, with its sequence
		number set to the sequence number in the ping command.
	</t>
	<t>
		If a connected and authenticated client has been waiting for a reply
		or for some other reason needs to determine if the server is still
		available. It can send a ping command.
		If the server is still available, it sends a ping reply.
		If it is no longer available for any reason, it sends a NotSupported
		reply.
	</t>
	<t>
		A client MUST NOT send a ping command if it is waiting
		the results of a previously sent ping command.
		If the server is ignoring PING commands, a reply will
		never happen.
	</t>
	<t>
		A client MUST NOT send a ping command more frequently
		than 90% of the SERVER_TIMEOUT value that the server sent
		in the CAPABILITY_POST command.
	</t>
	<t>
		Servers must give priority to ping commands.
		If possible, reply as soon as it receives the command.
	</t>
	<t>
		With servers that support PING, clients MUST NOT send any other
		command while wating for the PING reply.
	</t>
	<t>
		The server MAY consider too many ping commands as a malfunctioning
		or malicious client and terminate the connection.
	</t>
	<t>
		Servers that are not threaded or can not reply to simultaneous
		or overlapping commands, MUST NOT include PING in
		their post authentication capability command.
	</t>
</section>
